Preliminary Guide to the Linda Cropp papers, 1985-2006 MS2219
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Linda Cropp papers
1985-2006
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Cropp, Linda
MS2219
15 Linear Feet
The material in this collection reflect issues dealt with by Linda Cropp as a member of the Council of the District of Columbia from 1990-2006.
Restrictions on Access
This collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Donated in 2007
Historical or Biographical Note
Linda Cropp, born October 5, 1947, in Atlanta, Georgia, was a Democratic member of the Council of the District of Columbia from 1990-2006, where she served as the elected Council Chairman(1997-2006).
In 1980 she became the Ward 4 representative to the Board of Education, where she was later elected vice president and president.
In 1990, she was elected as an at-large member to the Council of the District of Columbia. Cropp also served as the Councilors representative to the Board of the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority. In that capacity, she held the position of Chair of the Budget Committee and played a major role in the expansion of the Metro Rail system.
In 1992, Cropp was selected to chair the Councilors Committee on Human Services. Under her oversight, the Department of Health was created. The re-organized agency focused on priorities including: controlling substance abuse, reducing infant mortality, eradicating tuberculosis, and fighting HIV/AIDS. She continued to chair the Committee after her 1994 re-election to the Council, but this time to an At-Large seat. With a desire to encourage self-sufficiency, Cropp introduced the Public Assistance Self-Sufficiency Program Amendment Act of 1996. She guided the act through the legislative process and oversaw the beginning of welfare reform in the District. In addition, Cropp oversaw the movement toward a comprehensive health care system that began with unification of D.C. General Hospital and the public health clinics.
Council colleagues chose her as acting chairman, in April 1997, following the death of David A. Clarke. After her victory in a special election, she was sworn in on August 8, 1997 as the first woman to chair the Council of the District of Columbia. In 1998, the voters of Washington, D.C. re-elected Linda Cropp to a full four-year term as Chairman of the Council. Again, by an overwhelming majority, Cropp was re-elected as Council Chairman in 2002. As chairman, Cropp has been instrumental in the District governments return to the John A. Wilson building, the historic home of the cities mayor and council.
On September 12, 2006, she lost the Democratic Primary for Mayor.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains reports, journals, testimonies, correspondence, memorabilia, photographs, certificates, awards, memorandums and proposals pertaining to issues dealt with by Linda Cropp as a member of the Council of the District of Columbia from 1990-2006. Topics covered include: Naturopathic medicine, Medical Malpractice, D.C. Hospitals including the Greater Southeast Community Hospital and National Medical Center, D.C. Public Schools, Tobacco Legislation and D.C. Baseball. The bulk of the materials date between 1994-2004 and tend to relate to the broad topic of D.C. health.
This collection was donated by Linda Cropp in 2007.
This collection is not fully processed. All the material arrived loose and has been foldered into broad topics. It is available for use, but may require more additional research time to understand the order. Please contact Special Collections for more information.
Collection Organization
Organized into 4 series: Healthcare legislation and research material, DC Council management and legislation, Awards, press and gifts, and Presentations and ceremonies.
Washington (D.C.); Photographs; Capitol Hill (Washington, D.C.); Public health; Politics and government; Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority; Cropp, Linda; Williams, Anthony
- Healthcare legislation and research material, 1999-2006; Series 1; 4 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  Material in this series relate to healthcare legislation in Washington DC and research for that legislation. This series dates from 1999-2006.
  Arrangement
  Maintains the original order from the donation.
  - Naturopathic Medicine, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Naturopathic Medicine, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Naturopathic Medicine, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Naturopathic Medicine, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Naturopathic Medicine, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Naturopathic Medicine, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Naturopathic Medicine, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Naturopathic Medicine, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Naturopathic Medicine, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Naturopathic Medicine, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Naturopathic Medicine, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Naturopahic Medicine, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Health Care, 2001-2005 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Health Care, 2003-2006 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Health Care/Medicaid, 2000-2006 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Health Care/D.C. Hospitals, 2002-2006 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Report D.C. Health and Hospitals, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Greater Southeast Community Hospital, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Greater Southeast Community Hospital, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - National Capital Medical Center, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - National Capital Medical Center/Howard University, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - National Capital Medical Center, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - National Capital Medical Center, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - D.C. General Hospital, 2000-2005 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - National Capital Medical Center, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - National Capital Medical Center, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - National Capital Medical Center, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Medical Malpractice, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Medical Malpractice Reform Act, 2003-2005 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Medical Malpractice/Health Care Reform Act 2004, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Medical Malpractice/Health Care Reform Act 2004, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Medical Malpractice/Health Care Reform Act 2004, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Medical Malpractice/Health Care Reform Act 2004, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Medical Malpractice/Health Care Reform Act 2004, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Small Employer and Individual Health Insurance Availability Act, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Newborn Screening Requirements Bill, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Greater Southeast Community Hospital and Healthcare Accountability Act Proposal, 2005 (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Medical Malepractice, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Briefing for D.C. City Council Committee on Human Services, 2001 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Health Care Systems Development Commission, 1999 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - National Capital Medical Center, 2006 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Resumes for Health Care System Development Commission, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Superintendent Search, 2005 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Greater Southeast Community Hospital Bankruptcy Part II, 2003 (Box 13, Folder 5)
- DC Council management and legislation, 1991-2006; Series 2; 7 Linear Feet
  The materials in this series are related to Washington DC legislation and DC Council management material. More specifically the material relates to children, the DC Waterfront, Tobacco and the Metro. The documents are dated between 1991-2006.
  - Proposed Budget and Financial Plan 2002-2003, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Memorandum of Understanding, 1997-2005 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Planned Resolutions/Acts 2006, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Permanent Guardianship for Grandparents, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Permanent Guardianship for Grandparents, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Permanent Guardianship for Grandparents, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Lincoln Heights/Richardson Dwellings Plan 2006, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Barry Farm/Dark Chester/Wade Road Plan 2006, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Southwest Waterfront Plan 2003, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Budget Act 2002-2004 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Planned Resolutions/Acts 2002 - 2006 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Planned Resolutions/Acts, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - D.C. Public Education, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - D.C. Public Education Rights, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - D.C. Public Schools, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - School Modernization, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Tax Revision Commission, 1997-1998 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Tobacco Securitization, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Tobacco Settlement Fund, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Tobacco Sales and Advertising, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Tobacco Settlement Funds, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Tobacco and Alcohol Sales to Minors, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Tobacco Sales to Minors, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Tobacco Settlement Trust Fund, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Securization Plan, 2001-2005 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - D.C. Baseball, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Comprehensive Plan Amendment Act 2006, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Agendas for Financial Responsibility and Management Authority, 1999-2001 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Financial Responsibility and Management Authority, 1993-2000 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Responsibility and Management Authority, 1999-2000 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Financial Responsibility and Management Authority, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - District Fiscal Crisis, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Holland and Knight Study Recommendations, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Management Reform Plan 1997 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Management Reform, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Control Board, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Committee Action Report, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Various Bills and Reports, 2001-2006 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - CASA for Children of D.C., undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Anthony Williams Report, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
    General note
    Chief Financial Officer Responsibilities
  - Voting Representation in Congress, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Comprehensive Plan Amendment Act 2006, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Emergency Preparedness in Nations Capital Report, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Emerging Technology Opportunity Development Act 2005, undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Congressional Black Caucus Foundation, undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - D.C. Education Compact Retreat, 2004 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - D.C. Education Compact Retreat, 2004 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Brussels Travel materials, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Legislative Agenda, 1999 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - American Express D.C. Culture Guide, 2001 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Legislative Agenda for Council of D.C., undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Agenda for the Council of D.C., 1999 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Questions and Answers about China, 1987 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Festivals and Folk Arts of Taiwan, undated (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - The Council of D.C. Period Nine, 1991-1992 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - D.C. Public Library folder, undated (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Town Hall Education Arts Recreation Campus folder, 2006 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Metro Resolutions of the Board of Directors, 2001 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - HIV/AIDS in the Nations Capital Report, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Leadership of Washington binder, undated (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Capital Budget Request, 2007 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - A Who's Who Salute to Dr. Dorothy Height, 2006 (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - D.C. FAIR act, undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Budget and Legislative Planning Meeting, 2003 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - The Anacostia Waterfront Corporation notebook, undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Domestic Preparedness Brieding to the City Council, 2001 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - D.C. Comprehensive Plan, Mayors Draft, 2006 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - National Capital Poison Center Certificate of Appreciation, undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - D.C. Coucil Group Photograph, 1997 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Awards, press and gifts, 1985-2006; Series 3; 3 Linear Feet
  Material in this series are related to awards, press and gifts given to Linda Cropp. Material dates between 1985-2006.
  - Newspaper clippings, magazines, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper clippings and magazines, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Metro Mania Boardgame, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Tobacco Settlement Certificate, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Council of D.C. Certificate of Award, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - D.C. Board of Education Certificate of Appreciation, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - D.C. Board of Education Passing of the Torch Award, 02/25/1988 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - D.C. Board of Education Passing of the Torch Award, 02/25/1988 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - D.C. Board of Education Certificate of Appreciation, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - National Senior Citizen Hall of Fame Award, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Stinger Family Certifiacte of Appreciation, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Repair Klingle Road Button and Canister, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - C.I.S. Pen and Letter Opener, undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Green Line to Greenbelt Gift, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Metrorail Anniversary Gift, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - D.C. City Council Group Photograph, undated (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Wallet size headshots, undated (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Church of the Advocate Quilt Gift, 2004 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Snow in America book, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Signed by author
  - The True Size of Government, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    Signed by Author
  - Guidebook to the 108th, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - City Within a City Greater U st. Heritage Trail brochure, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - The History of Asbury United Methodist Church book, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - The National Congress of Black Women 22nd Annual Awards Celebration booklet, 2006 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Harman Center for the Arts booklet, undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Burned CD labeled Filemaker, undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - National Rainbow Coalition Statehood Campaign magazine, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - John Wilson Building pamphlette, undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Howard University Charter Day Dinner invitation, 1999 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Certificate of Need Reform Work Group Resource Book, 2002 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Educational Learning Center Certificate of Appreciation, 1995 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - D.C. Council Group Photograph, Circa 1990-2006 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Adult Education Collage, 2005 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - St. Coletta of Greater Washington thank you card, undated (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Marriott Washington Convention Center Hotel, undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
- Presentations and ceremonies, 1991-2006; Series 4; 2 Linear Feet
  Material in this folder are related to presentaions given by Linda Cropp and ceremonies that she attended. Materials in this series are dated between 1991-2006.
  - VHS tape, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - VHS tape, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - VHS tape, 2002 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - VHS tape City Cable 13 Update, undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - VHS tape WDC City Cuncil Public Oversight Hearing, 2003 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - VHS tape Mayor Williams Baseball and Economic Opportunity Address, 2004 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - VHS tape Mayor Inagural Swearing in Ceremony part 1, 2003 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - VHS tape Mayor Inaugural Swearing in Ceremony part 2, undated (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - VHS tape Walter Washington: Champion of Democracy, undated (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - VHS tape WB NOW, 2005 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - VHS tape WB NOW, 2004 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - VHS tape the History Makers, 2005 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - VHS tape Rev. Jesse L. Jackson at Metropolitan Baptist Church, 2002 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - VHS tape Trachtenberg Scholars, 2002 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - VHS tape WDC City Council Profile, 2002 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - VHS tape Joint Scholarship Awards Program, undated (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - VHS tape Baseball Proposal, 2004 (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - VHS tape Welcome Home, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Presentation to Fitch Ratings, 2002 (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Presentation to Standard and Poors's, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - Presentation to Moody's Investors Service, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - Presentation to Fitch Ratings, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - The Anacostia Waterfront Corporation's Presentation to Linda Cropp, 2006 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Medical Liability Reform in D.C. Proposal, undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - H Street NE Strategic Development Plan, 2003 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - H Street NE Development and Design Guidelines, 2003 (Box 14, Folder 8)